Guide to the Frank Stanford Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Frank Stanford papers
1960-2000
1970-1993
YCAL MSS 295
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.5
(9 boxes)
The collection consists of material created and accumulated by Frank Stanford, as well as material created and accumulated after Stanford's death by C. D. Wright in her role as co-executor of his estate and as editor of Lost Roads Publishers. Included are Stanford's writings, which comprise manuscripts and drafts of poems and prose, some of which are C. D. Wright's copies, and notebooks; correspondence received by Stanford from editors, publishers, and writers; correspondence relating to Stanford and Lost Roads Publishers received by C. D. Wright; personal and press business records; a small amount of photographs; and printed material. The material documents Stanford's work as a poet and publisher, his involvement in filmmaking, aspects of the initial operation of Lost Roads Publishers, and the posthumous publication, reception, and study of Stanford's work.
Stanford, Frank, 1949-1978
Wright, C. D., 1949-2016
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Forrest Gander and C. D. Wright, 2008, and purchased from C. D. Wright on the Alfred Z. Baker, Jr. Fund, 2012.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 8 (computer disks) and Box 9 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Associated Material
Related material can found in Lost Roads Publisher Records, Uncat MSS 938 and Uncat MSS 1286.
Frank Stanford (1948-1978)
Frank Stanford was born in southeast Mississippi in 1948. In the following year he was adopted by Dorothy Gilbert, and in 1952 relocated to Arkansas when Gilbert married Albert Franklin Stanford. Remembered as a bright and athletic child in his early youth, the young Frank Stanford was greatly affected by the knowledge of his adoption. He entered the University of Arkansas in 1967 as a student of Civil Engineering, but later on switched to study literature, and was well known in the Fayetteville literary community for his poetry. He wrote poems for the student literary magazine, Preview, and many of the early poems following his college years were published in journals such as Field, Ironwood, and American Poetry Review.
Stanford left college without earning a degree. In 1970 he met Irving Broughton, editor and publisher of Mill Mountain Press, who published Stanford's first book, The Singing Knives. Between 1970-76, Mill Mountain published five more of Stanford's books. Also in the early 70s, Broughton and Stanford made a documentary film about Stanford's work and life. The film, It Wasn't a Dream it Was a Flood, won the Best Experimental Film Award at the West Coast Film Festival in 1975. The following year saw the birth of Stanford's own publishing company, Lost Roads Publishers. Lost Roads sought to "reclaim the landscape of American poetry" by publishing little known authors, whom the poet C.D. Wright, succeeding Stanford as editor, called the "the beautiful wild poets we grow from the road." In 1977, Lost Roads Publishers and Mill Mountain Press joint-published Stanford's epic poem, The Battlefield Where the Moon Says I Love You, a manuscript of over 15,000 lines of poetry that Stanford had been working on sporadically since his early teenage years.
Stanford was well aware of the unique sensitivity that marked him apart from others even in childhood. "When the rest of you / Were being children / I became a monk / To my own listening / Imagination." Elsewhere, Stanford speaks of Death, which he imagines as a fisherman in a boat: "Young as I am I / Hold light for this boat." Amongst Stanford's most powerful poems are his reflections on this shadow from which none return. Franz Wright called him "one of the great voices of Death." With uncanny insight and beauty, Stanford's poems often seek to portray and imagine Death, which was, in Wright's words, "his biggest love affair."
On June 3 1978, at the age of 29, Stanford took his own life in his home in Fayetteville, Arkansas. His chapbook Crib Death came out shortly afterwards. Lost Roads published more of his poems in You in 1979, and a collection of his short fiction Conditions Uncertain And Likely To Pass Away in 1990. The following year the University of Arkansas Press published The Light the Dead See: Selected Poems of Frank Stanford.
Biographical note prepared by Shu-Han Luo, Yale College '09.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of material created and accumulated by Frank Stanford, as well as material created and accumulated after Stanford's death by C. D. Wright in her role as co-executor of his estate and as editor of Lost Roads Publishers. Included are Stanford's writings, which comprise manuscripts and drafts of poems and prose, some of which are C. D. Wright's copies, and notebooks; correspondence received by Stanford from editors, publishers, and writers; correspondence relating to Stanford and Lost Roads Publishers received by C. D. Wright; personal and press business records; a small amount of photographs; and printed material. The material documents Stanford's work as a poet and publisher, his involvement in filmmaking, aspects of the initial operation of Lost Roads Publishers, and the posthumous publication, reception, and study of Stanford's work.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence and Other Papers. II. Writings and Other Papers. III. October 2012 Acquisition.
American poetry -- 20th Century; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Publishers and publishing -- United States -- 20th Century; Stanford, Frank, 1949-1978; Wright, C. D., 1949-2016; Lost Roads Publishers
- Correspondence and Other Papers, Series I; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Files are largely arranged in the order in which they were received.
  - Drawer 1 List (Box 1)
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Correspondence between C. D. Wright and Carrie Rogers (Stanford's niece), 2000 (Box 1)
  - Lists of File Drawers Contents (Box 1)
  - 2 Issues of "The Grapevine", 1977 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence to Stanford - Babi, Jim, 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence to Stanford - Broughton, Irv, 1971-1973; 2 (Box 1)
  - Murray Shugars/FS Thesis, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence to C. D. Wright - Letters from Readers, 1978-1997; 2 (Box 1)
  - Bibliography/Bio Notes (Box 1)
  - Correspondence to Stanford re: Submissions, solicitations, etc., 1971-1977 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence to C. D. Wright - Carpenter, Bill, 1988-1991 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence to Stanford - Cuddihy, Michael, 1973-1976, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence to Stanford - Dugan, Alan, 1971-1977 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Fuhrmann, Nicholas, 1979, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence to Stanford - Ben Kimpel re: Battlefield (Box 1)
  - Correspondence to C. D. Wright - Launius, Carl, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence to Stanford - McKernan, John, 1973-1978 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence to Stanford - Stafford, William, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Dorothy Stanford to C. D. Wright, 2 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence to Stanford - Walker, David, 1973-1975, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Richard Wilbur, Clipping (Box 1)
  - Joan Williams to C.D. and Stanford, 1989 February 17 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Wright, Ernie (Box 1)
  - re: work of FS (Box 2)
  - Stanford Reviews (Box 2)
  - Submissions, Publication Record, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Letters to Lost Roads Authors (from Stanford), 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence to C.D. Wright - Seluzicki, Charles, Rare Book Dealer, 1981 (Box 2)
  - "Irv Brought Talks with Frank Stanford," typescript, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Awards (relating to various award competitions), 1975-1991 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence to Stanford, Films and Books (Box 2)
  - Film Information (Box 2)
  - Film Grant and "Gospel Bird", 1976 (Box 2)
  - South Africa and other politics (Box 2)
  - Lost Roads Press business, 1974-1978 (Box 2)
  - 1975 tax returns (Box 2)
  - Awards (Box 2)
  - Publishing Costs/Personal Business, 1975-1979 (Box 2)
  - Surveying Business (Chason Tilex), 1974-1978 (Box 2)
  - The Grapevine obit issue, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Stanford/Selected Poems/U. of Arkansas, 1991-1993 (Box 2)
  - Obit/Elegy by Stan and Stokesbury (Box 2)
  - Obit/hakr/etc. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence re: work of Stanford, 1983-1992 (Box 2)
  - June News Releases, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Birth (information regarding Stanford's birth), 2 (Box 2)
- Writings and Other Papers, Series II; (4 boxes)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 9 contains audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - List Drawer 2 (Box 3)
  - Field Talk (Box 3)
  - Grapevine (2 issues) (Box 3)
  - Extra Copies from uncollected poems (Box 3)
  - YOU (x2) (Box 3)
  - YOU x2 (Box 3)
  - YOU x3 (Box 3)
  - YOU (Box 3)
  - Conditions Uncertain and Likely to Pass Away: Stories of Frank Stanford, circa 1985; 2 (Box 3)
  - Tales A-F (Box 3)
  - Tales H-M (Box 3)
  - Tales S-W (Box 3)
  - Letters to Fr. Jerome, re: translation of Bertolucci work (Box 3)
  - Poetry Fragment, Typed (Box 3)
  - Conditions Uncertain Galley (Box 3)
  - The Singing Knives (Box 3)
  - To Frank and C. D., 1975-1977 (Box 3)
  - Originals (Box 3)
  - Poems to Ginny's Admin (Box 3)
  - [Poetry as Process] (Box 3)
  - The Battlefield (Box 3)
  - To Ginny's Admin Stories and Poems, 2 (Box 3)
  - Prose Fragments (Box 3)
  - [notes and poems] (Box 4)
  - Uncollected (Box 4)
  - Approacheth the Ship... (Box 4)
  - Mad Dogs (Box 4)
  - Handwritten Notes - Fragments (Box 4)
  - Wounds (Box 4)
  - Smoking Grapevine (Box 4)
  - Automatic Co-pilot Adaptations and Translations (Box 4)
  - Poems, manuscripts (Box 4)
  - Last Panther in the Ozarks (Box 4)
  - Floor Extras (Box 4)
  - From Plain Songs (Box 4)
  - List Drawer 3 (Box 4)
  - Printed Material, 4 (Box 4)
  - List Drawer 4 (Box 4)
  - Jazz Impressions (Box 4)
  - Poster Ups, 3 (Box 4)
  - Poster Ups, 2 (Box 5)
  - Ephemera (Box 5)
  - Untitled, undated; 1; This reel is completely blank. It has not been digitized. (Box 9, Item barcode 39002099369655)
    Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - "A Lost Roads Crossing" (audiotape reel), 1978 October 23; 1; 00:53:22 (Box 9, Item barcode 39002099369663)
    Scope and Contents
    Contents include lyrics for: "Spell" by F. Stanford.
  - Land Surveyor Stamp (Box 5)
  - Photographs (Box 5)
  - St. Francis and the Wolf, 2 (Box 5)
  - Sound Recording Tape (Box 5)
  - Printed Material (Box 5)
  - Notebooks, YOU, 2 (Box 5)
  - Notebooks, Singing Knives, 2 (Box 5)
  - Collected Poems by Alan Dugan, Annotated (Box 5)
  - The Singing Knives, C. D. Wright's original copy (Box 5)
  - Open Places, with letter from Stanford to Donald Justice inside, 1972 (Box 5)
  - Manuscript items removed from books (Box 5)
- October 2012 Acquisition, 1974-2000; 0.5; (3 boxes)
  - Awards, 1981, undated (Box 6)
  - Decree of adoption documents, correspondence, and notes (Box 6)
  - Correspondence and event posters (Box 6)
  - Oxford American (Box 6)
    Editor Attila Berry's correspondence with C. D. Wright; proofs.
  - Publications, 1974-2000 (Box 6)
    Publications, clippings, and photocopies containing Stanford's work.
  - Posters and photograph of an excavation (Box 7 (Oversize))
  - Restricted fragile
    - Computer media, 3 CD-Rs (Box 8)
      CD-Rs contain Frank Stanford photographs.
      Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.